<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lingnik : Taylor J. Meek</title>
    <description>Taylor is a software engineer and linguist living in Portland, OR who fancies the outdoors. He currently works for Iberdrola Renewables, the world&#39;s largest wind power owner-operator, as a SCADA analyst.</description>
    <link>http://lingnik.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lingnik.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Bitcasa to Early Adopters: Pay More for Less or Leave</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At TechCrunch Disrupt on September 12th, 2011, Bitcasa &lt;a href=&quot;http://thenextweb.com/apps/2011/09/23/bitcasa-infinite-storage-comes-to-your-desktop-but-so-do-big-questions/&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt; their encrypted “Infinite Drive” cloud storage offering for $10/month (after the end of their beta program). Last year, on November 19, 2013, the company announced that it was increasing the price for its Infinite plan from $99/year to $999/year, but would allow existing Infinite users to keep paying $99/year at the expense of not receiving new features, such as Bitcasa’s Linux client. Today, Bitcasa has announced that they are severing the cord permanently for their early adopters by forcing all Infinite Drive customers onto a non-infinite plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From their &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.bitcasa.com/hc/en-us/articles/203936983&quot;&gt;FAQ page&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20141022214551/https://support.bitcasa.com/hc/en-us/articles/203936983&quot;&gt;here’s a cached version&lt;/a&gt;, since Bitcasa tends to delete pages and commentary when it turns negative) describing the change of policy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bitcasa will no longer offer or support Infinite subscription plans. Current Infinite users must choose a new plan and accompanying storage limit. To meet the needs of users that require more than 5TB of storage, we are changing the storage limit for the Pro plan from 5TB to 10TB. Pricing for the Pro plan will increase from $49 per month to $99 per month for new subscriptions. These changes will not affect existing users. Existing Pro subscribers will continue on their current pricing and 5TB of storage. Existing Pro subscribers will also auto-renew at their current pricing and 5TB of storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--adsense-bitcasa1--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Existing users have until November 15, 2014 to choose a new plan or to download their files and delete their account. Plans start at $10/month or $99/year for 1TB; or $99/month or $999/year for 10TB. These prices are in line with alternative offerings from Google and Dropbox, but higher than OneDrive. But if you choose not to transition to a new plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We understand that some users may not want to continue using the service. As always, your data is yours and you are free to download it and take it with you at any time. […] Should you do nothing, your account will be closed and all data deleted on November 15, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit (2014-10-23 8:20AM): I previously reported that Bitcasa was doing away with their Infinite storage last year; in fact, they increased the price for their Infinite plan from $99/year to $999/year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 11:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2014/10/22/bitcasa-to-early-adopters-pay-more-for-less-or-leave.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2014/10/22/bitcasa-to-early-adopters-pay-more-for-less-or-leave.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Earl--Sqigle&#39;s crowdfunded tablet project--legitimate? Probably.</title>
        <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Full disclosure:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;I was an early backer of Earl. Like several other (of their 2,200+) backers, I have followed the story of Earl through their forums, sparse Twitter updates, and even sparser website updates. Like a small minority of those followers, I had in recent months also started to worry that this whole campaign was never going to be realized — or worse, that it was a straight scam. I finally reached the limit of my own patience, and emailed Sqigle’s CEO–Jon Perry–to get the scoop, and he took the time to (politely) respond to my (unexpectedly antagonistic, in retrospect) email. Here’s what I found out.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, at the beginning of May, Jonathan Perry was fortunate to realize the beginning of a journey. He wouldn’t have done it without the backers of his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetearl.com/&quot;&gt;crowdfunded project&lt;/a&gt;, Earl (named after his dog), the waterproof, solar-powered outdoor-activity-inspired tablet with ham radio and GMRS/FRS support, free topo maps… I’m sure I’m leaving out something… It’s a fairly ambitious product that sounded like a hiker’s dream. Nothing like it exists on the market today. (Especially at a $299 price point for preorders.) Like all crowdfunded projects, however, there are risks, and Earl isn’t in backers’ hands yet — this Wednesday will be the 16-month-mark of Earl’s campaign reaching its $250,000 goal. Jonathan’s team is still pushing forward with their ambitious product, and looking towards the future they hope their hardware startup will have in post-production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;crowdfunding-is-risky-business&quot;&gt;Crowdfunding is Risky Business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not unexpected for a crowdfunding project to take longer than expected, or to fail entirely. CNN Money posted a chart&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the 50 top-funded Kickstarter projects through November 2012. Of those 50, only 8 (16%) shipped on-time, leaving 84% of projects delayed. Fox News suggests&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the delay rate may be as high as 75%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1523379957/oculus-rift-step-into-the-game&quot;&gt;Oculus Rift&lt;/a&gt; hadn’t even shipped as of the time of their writing, but since have. In Oculus Rift’s case, Facebook later acquired them for $2bn in mid-2014, less than two years after their wildly successful (but heavily delayed) crowdfunding campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because some make it doesn’t mean that all do. Neal Stephenson’s crowdfunded swordplay game recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/260688528/clang/posts/989911&quot;&gt;posted their final update&lt;/a&gt;, throwing in the towel on 9,023 backers’ $526,125 two years after they were funded and the money has been all spent on what amounts to a game that “wasn’t very fun to play.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These risks haven’t stop backers from funding projects, though. According to a Massolution report published on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crowdsourcing.org/editorial/2013cf-crowdfunding-outlook-report/26448&quot;&gt;Crowdsourcing.org&lt;/a&gt;, $2.7bn was crowdfunded in 2012, and that number was expected to grow to $5.1bn in 2013. And the World Bank expects crowdfunding to grow to $93bn by 2025.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;earls-red-flags&quot;&gt;Earl’s Red Flags&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why has Earl received criticism, and is it warranted? Some of these complaints are genuine and warranted, but others turn out to be falsehoods spawned from a vacuum of backer communication. From reading the &lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.meetearl.com/&quot;&gt;forums&lt;/a&gt; and following &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%40meetearl&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;updates on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, complainants fall into three main categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earl’s release date keeps getting pushed back&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earl’s team isn’t providing updates frequently enough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This whole Earl thing feels like a scam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I found out by talking to Jon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-slip&quot;&gt;Release Slip&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, crowdfunding projects have up to an 84% chance of slipping deadlines. Earl is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earl’s flaw, in this case, comes from Jon’s initial inexperience with the process. He shared the campaign’s inception with me: “The original idea when I started prototyping some ereaders together at my house was to run a Kickstarter.” Jon shared with me that they chose not to go with a platform like Kickstarter or Indiegogo because they wanted more creative control of the page layout. Further, at the time all they had was a prototype and some renderings, “Since I didn’t have a fully functional prototype in hand I didn’t think a video would do Earl justice.” (The renderings would have violated Kickstarter’s policies.) Kickstarter and Indiegogo would also take a cut of the funds, making Jon’s job even more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I built the site and posted it to my Facebook and within a few days people started preordering Earl. I actually rushed to get some press stuff together, but the internet had organically taken our campaign and ran us around the world a few times.” And then, of course, reality caught up with him. “It’s taken a whole heck of a lot longer than I ever expected.” So what caused the delays? Jon realized he needed outside help to build twice as many Earls as he planned, “Taking on a project of this magnitude without prior experience required the help of a few contracted firms.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Jon was living in the Seattle area, and the Shenzhen manufacturers were half a world away. “Anyone that has had issues manufacturing abroad can relate to some of the setbacks we’ve encountered. Most of the problems could have been resolved much sooner, unfortunately these teams require more hands on from our team to keep things going forward.”, he explains, “700k is not very much to go by, but we’re making it work. Unfortunately it doesn’t leave room for a local team right now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/earl/earl-jon-may01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Earl lives!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since those delays, backer updates show that development is back on track (although they routinely experience minor setbacks from their vendors), and Earl has (another) timeline up. The device is currently moving towards certification from the FCC and their Canadian, European, and Oceania counterparts. Software engineering is in full swing, too; from the latest update: “I took the opportunity to fly out to Delhi to meet with our software development team. They’ve been working hard to get all the features we need integrated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;crowdfunding-updates&quot;&gt;Crowdfunding Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these situations, there seems to be a direct correlation between frequency of backer updates and campaign success (and, I would personally argue, backer satisfaction). &lt;a href=&quot;http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~wenhuang/pub/CHI2014_Xu.pdf&quot;&gt;Seriously, people study these things these days.&lt;/a&gt; But in Earl’s case, early communication slipped way to the occasional monthly update, and backer annoyance became a common thread of Twitter updates, as backers began probing the company to post updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;dipity_embed&quot; style=&quot;width:800px&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;http://www.dipity.com/lingnik/Meet-Earl/?mode=embed&amp;amp;z=2yr#tl&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dipity.com/lingnik/Meet-Earl/&quot;&gt;Meet Earl&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://dipity.com/&quot;&gt;Dipity&lt;/a&gt;
 - &lt;em&gt;The above timeline shows Earl’s email updates and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetearl.com/updates/&quot;&gt;updates posted to their website&lt;/a&gt;, which have grown further and further apart over time. Email updates have ceased entirely.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earl’s updates were slower than some folks wanted, even from the beginning, and Earl acknowledged that by apologizing time and time again. With each update came additional promises, and often, those promises included increased frequency of updates. However, time and time again those more frequent updates never materialized. “This time last year I was certain I would have the retail version in my hand by summer,” Jon told me in his email, “Though I may not be the most punctual when it comes to communication, it’s challenging trying to juggle so many things at once.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon’s Twitter followers are hard to appease, and routinely remind Jon that updates are due on his website when more than 30 days have elapsed… or sometimes sooner. Posters on his forums are even more challenging, though, with many scathing posts faced down by a calm Sqiqle CEO and his backer/supporters. It seems his backers are accustomed to a certain level of service, and don’t feel like they’re getting it. 
&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/earl/earl-twitter-updates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Twitter anger&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-is-sqigle-earl-and-jon-perry&quot;&gt;Who is Sqigle, Earl, and Jon Perry?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since beginning the execution phase of the campaign, Jon has has been a nomad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Officially at this time, we do not have an office. I run virtually as I’ve been living in Hong Kong most of the past year and when I’m in the states, I’m in either LA, SLC, SF or Seattle. None of which I have an apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the liberty of digging deeper into the company building Earl–Sqigle–as well as its founder, Jon Perry. Jon was a little taken aback by the details I uncovered. &lt;em&gt;(Most of which I won’t share here, out of concerns for the privacy of his friends and family, as well as some confidentiality concerns with his manufacturing partners.)&lt;/em&gt; But by his own account, “I accepted this public position when we ran our campaign. I’m just not used to people “googling” me yet, not mad, just feels weird.” Despite his apprehension, he addressed each of my concerns, probably from one of his many living room offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“LA is home to one of my old friends that helps with the business side, researching the market and helping write a pitch for VC investments. Salt Lake City, where I resided for a few years, is where the dog Earl has been living while I’m away, with an old friend.” In San Francisco, there’s another friend/business partner: “He’s one of the people that helped me handle things during the campaign and [he’ll be helping with] marketing and support in the next coming months.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that Jon’s manufacturing partner is in Shenzhen, Hong Kong, China, one of the fastest growing cities in the world and home to a sizable manufacturing district&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. His software engineering partner is based out of Delhi, India. I did some web sleuthing after Jon shared some details on their manufacturing side with me. Although he can’t publicly share the name of the partners he’s doing business with, I can assure you that they exist, and that these people are not robots, college students, or CGI-rendered people:
&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/earl/earl-china-team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;real Chinese manufacturing experts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jon Perry and his Chinese manufacturing experts (who are not CGI-rendered)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, Jon addressed the critical eye I afforded him politely and openly, including the private aspects of his life I had no business asking about to verify his identity. Even the previous business ventures of his that I unearthed were explained rationally. Jon’s got an entrepreneurial spirit, and the attitude to push through problems in his businesses. He used to sell &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webmd.com/diet/hcg-and-weight-loss&quot;&gt;HCG dietary supplements&lt;/a&gt;, did a brisk business in buying iPhones here in the US and reselling them overseas (before Apple set a 2-phone limit), and resold used sporting goods, before he started tinkering with ereaders and solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when I probed him on how he’s spending his time, and his background, we get another window into the infrequent updates: “I’ve been spending most of my free time prepping for a VC round this coming November in Dublin where we’ve been asked to attend the Web Summit. I’m sure investors will be asking similar questions. While I can see how this campaign could look fraudulent, it probably wouldn’t be so smart to stick around.” In the age of the internet, it’s possible to verify anybody’s electronic persona against their offline identity, and Jon’s no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary----or-earls-probably-legit-after-all&quot;&gt;Summary – Or, Earl’s Probably Legit After All&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sqigle is a real company, registered in Washington State, and the details about Jon and his startup I uncovered leave me with no other impression than that Earl is in development and nearing production, and that Jon has every intention to bring it not only to his backers’ hands, but also into retail stores. My personal impression is that Jon’s a busy guy trying to juggle a startup with the support of a close handful of co-founders and a few overseas contract engineering companies. He committed to a project without knowing the full extent to which his life would be consumed by Earl. He’s built a manufacturing, software engineering, and marketing company around himself with the scrappy cash his backers provided him. He’s flown himself to China and all over the US to try to make sure this project is a success, and put his life on hold to realize the dream he kicked off in the summer of 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Jon told me, “We’re only here because backers like you helped us get a start.” Which is the exact same story other crowdfunding projects have repeated – those that have succeeded, those that haven’t, and those that haven’t – yet. I’m still hopeful with this one. But if you aren’t, Jon is prepared for that too: “I stick by our refund policy, if at anytime you want out, let us know.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time will tell if Jon’s team starts updating more frequently, and whether the campaign bears fruit, but Jon has something to look forward to at the end of this adventure (and hopefully, the beginning of his next):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everyone here is working extremely hard so that we can deliver the best version of Earl to each of you and so Jon can get back home to play with the real Earl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../assets/earl/earl-home.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;the real Earl&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/interactive/technology/kickstarter-projects-shipping/&quot;&gt;http://money.cnn.com/interactive/technology/kickstarter-projects-shipping/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foxnews.com/tech/2013/08/06/kickstopped-75-percent-projects-delayed-on-crowdfunding-site/&quot;&gt;http://www.foxnews.com/tech/2013/08/06/kickstopped-75-percent-projects-delayed-on-crowdfunding-site/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pbs.org/mediashift/2013/12/world-bank-crowdfunding-investment-market-to-hit-93-billion-by-2025/&quot;&gt;http://www.pbs.org/mediashift/2013/12/world-bank-crowdfunding-investment-market-to-hit-93-billion-by-2025/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shenzhen&quot;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shenzhen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2014 13:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2014/09/22/is-earl-sqigles-crowdfunded-tablet-project-legitimate.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2014/09/22/is-earl-sqigles-crowdfunded-tablet-project-legitimate.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reverse Engineering the Yaesu VX-8DR GPS Interface</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2014-04-13&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dfannin&quot;&gt;David Fannin&lt;/a&gt; built on this work and came up with some Arduino code that interfaces between the VX-8DR and a Ublox GPS module. You can see more information at his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dfannin/arduino-vx8r-gps&quot;&gt;project’s github page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#incompatible-proprietary-and-non-standard&quot;&gt;Incompatible, Proprietary, and Non-Standard&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#garmin-gpsmap-60csx-serial-interface&quot;&gt;Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx Serial Interface&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yaesu-vx-8dr-serial-interface&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR Serial Interface&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sending-gps-nmea-strings-to-the-yaesu-vx-8dr&quot;&gt;Sending GPS NMEA Strings to the Yaesu VX-8DR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-nmea-0183-standard&quot;&gt;The NMEA 0183 Standard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#vx-8dr-nmea-handshake&quot;&gt;VX-8DR NMEA Handshake&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#nmea-address-field&quot;&gt;NMEA Address Field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#proprietary-message-codes&quot;&gt;Proprietary Message Codes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gpgga-messages---gps-time-position-and-fix-data&quot;&gt;$GPGGA Messages - GPS Time, Position, and Fix Data&lt;/a&gt;        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#our-garmin-gpgga-sample&quot;&gt;Our Garmin $GPGGA Sample&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gprmc-messages---gnss-time-date-position-course-and-speed&quot;&gt;$GPRMC Messages - GNSS Time, Date, Position, Course, and Speed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#if-it-doesnt-conform-what-is-the-right-way-to-do-it&quot;&gt;If it doesn’t conform, what is the right way to do it?&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#vx8r-yahoo-group&quot;&gt;VX8R Yahoo Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yaesu-vx-8dr-gpgga-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPGGA NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yaesu-vx-8dr-gprmc-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPRMC NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yaesu-vx-8dr-gpzda-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPZDA NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-different-is-the-yaesu-from-the-garmin&quot;&gt;How different is the Yaesu from the Garmin?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-about-those-other-messages-the-yaesu-supports&quot;&gt;What about those other messages the Yaesu supports?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#yaesu-vx-8dr-nmea-controller&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR NMEA Controller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally got my Technician Class amateur radio operator license (KG7BBG) last week, and I’ve been sitting on a Yaesu VX-8DR radio for about a year waiting to use it until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first time on the air was an APRS beacon transmission, which was cool and all, getting to see my location at &lt;a href=&quot;http://aprs.fi/info/a/KG7BBG-7&quot;&gt;aprs.fi&lt;/a&gt;. However, the VX-8DR is notoriously cumbersome to manually enter latitude and longitude coordinates. The OEM GPS module for this radio retails at $160 for the module and mount, and the internal antenna is notorious for being mounted in such a way that if you wanted to get good coverage, you would have to lay the radio down on its back.&lt;a href=&quot;http://stuartl.longlandclan.yi.org/blog/2012/03/24/yaesu-vx8dr/&quot;&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in one of my boxes, however, is a Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx GPS receiver with an RS232 serial interface (with a proprietary connector) for NMEA data. So naturally, I want to use this piece of equipment I already have in lieu of spending another $160 for something that doesn’t work very well. This does mean that using GPS-fed APRS will be a little more cumbersome, since I’ll have to carry a second piece of equipment (and also, as I think we’ll see, a converter module).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;incompatible-proprietary-and-non-standard&quot;&gt;Incompatible, Proprietary, and Non-Standard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first discovery I had was that the serial interfaces on these two devices is incompatible, and cannot be connected together directly. But before we get to that, here’s some technical information on these two devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;garmin-gpsmap-60csx-serial-interface&quot;&gt;Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx Serial Interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Garmin 60CSx has a round plug on the back with a four-pin interface. This is a proprietary interface which has several &lt;a href=&quot;https://buy.garmin.com/shop/shop.do?pID=310&quot;&gt;cabling options&lt;/a&gt;, such as a bare cable (010-10082-00, $20.83 on Amazon) ready for custom wiring integrations.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/garmin-gpsmap-60csx-serial-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx Serial Interface Pinout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to mock this up, I built a simple interface cable out of the hand-hacked equivalent of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/products/824&quot;&gt;Adafruit’s female-male extension jumper wires&lt;/a&gt;. (I only had male-male and female-female, so I soldered half of a male to half of a female.) The white wire in this photo is the transmit pin from the Garmin, and the black wire is ground.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/Garmin_Interface_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx Serial Connection Mockup to MOXA UPort 1150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this, I was able to connect this to my PC using an RS232 serial-to-USB adapter, and, using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moxa.com/product/download_pcommlite_info.htm&quot;&gt;PComm Lite Terminal Emulator from MOXA&lt;/a&gt;, capture the NMEA strings off the device. I configured the 60CSx (Setup&amp;gt;Interfaces) to output NMEA formatted data and in the advanced settings (Menu&amp;gt;Advanced NMEA Setup), enabled only GPS Status, Waypoint/Route, and left Lat/Lon precision at 4 digits. The 60CSx only supports 4800 baud on the NMEA serial interface, so I used the settings 4800/8/N/1 in PComm, and retrieved the following raw data. I’ve highlighted the relevant strings for what we’ll need later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRTE,1,1,c,*37
$GPRMC,024006,A,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,3.3,26.2,100213,17.4,E,D*08
$GPRMB,A,,,,,,,,,,,,V,D*19
$GPGGA,024006,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,07,1.6,65.5,M,-20.2,M,,*49
$GPGSA,A,3,,03,,,07,08,10,13,16,,23,,1.8,1.6,0.9*3C
$GPGSV,3,1,12,02,01,290,00,03,27,101,18,05,07,327,00,06,23,079,00*72
$GPGSV,3,2,12,07,60,277,33,08,30,259,23,10,43,280,21,13,78,098,17*79
$GPGSV,3,3,12,16,36,050,15,19,11,120,00,23,49,123,16,48,36,194,30*7F
$GPGLL,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,024006,A,D*51
$GPBOD,,T,,M,,*47
$GPVTG,26.2,T,8.7,M,3.3,N,6.1,K,D*18
$HCHDG,8.7,,,17.4,E*14
$GPRTE,1,1,c,*37
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 60CSx supports NMEA 0183 version 3.01, and the manual goes more into detail on the sentences it supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yaesu-vx-8dr-serial-interface&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR Serial Interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yaesu VX-8DR has a round plug on the top with seven-pin interface. This is a proprietary interface with several &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.universal-radio.com/catalog/ht/0008.html&quot;&gt;cabling options&lt;/a&gt;, such as a bare cable (CT-M11, $23.95 on Universal Radio) ready for custom wiring integrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/yaesu-ct-m11-cable-pin-numbers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pin numbers of Yaesu VX-8DR radio transceiver microphone/serial/gps connector&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/yaesu-vx-8dr-mic-pinout.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pinout table of pin numbers and purpose for Yaesu VX-8DR radio transceiver microphone/serial/gps connector&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/yaesu-ct-m11-cable-pinout.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wire diagram of Yaesu CT-M11 cable connected to Yaesu VX-8DR radio transceiver&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to mock this up, I used a Maxton RPC-Y8R-UF programming cable I picked up from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.g4hfq.co.uk/links.html&quot;&gt;G4HFQ&lt;/a&gt; (I can’t find the link to buy these cables on his site anymore, however). This is essentially an FTDI cable, which in this case is a three-wire interface (Ground, Rx, and Tx) at 3.3V levels. RS232 is a 5V%2B interface, which exposes the incompatibility between these two devices. The CT-M11 cable from Yaesu exposes all of the pins, which is useful for integrating a custom microphone/speaker interface along with GPS/programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/Yaesu_Cable_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Maxton RPC-Y8R-UF cable used to connect to Yaesu VX-8DR over serial TTL&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I can connect the VX-8DR to my PC and, using PComm, transmit data to the radio over serial. Configuration settings are 9600/8/N/1 (NOT 4800 baud, another point of incompatibility between these two devices). Enter the APRS GPS menu (press ‘MENU’ once). You will see a compass with no arrow and empty coordinate fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sending-gps-nmea-strings-to-the-yaesu-vx-8dr&quot;&gt;Sending GPS NMEA Strings to the Yaesu VX-8DR&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we can connect to the VX-8DR over 9600-baud 3.3V FTDI serial, we can send a string to the device with PComm Lite. Let’s try the NMEA $GPGGA string from the Garmin directly – paste it (CTRL%2BALT%2BP) into the session, and press ENTER to send it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,013622,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,09,0.9,00078,M,0020,M,,*49
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yaesu spits out some information the first time you send it a serial message. Also, the Yaesu displays something on its display!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/Yaesu_Bad_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of Yaesu VX-8DR radio transceiver showing garbage data after receiving improper GPS NMEA sentence&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s weird. The latitude and longitude are garbled, and speed/altitude are empty. Time to figure out what we sent means, and what we received means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-nmea-0183-standard&quot;&gt;The NMEA 0183 Standard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NMEA 0183 standard is a product of the National Marine Electronics Association. It’s a proprietary standard, and costs $250 to obtain. Thanks to the wonders of the internet, this is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=nmea%2B0183%2Bversion%2B3.01%2Bfiletype%3Apdf&quot;&gt;major&lt;/a&gt; hindrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained before, the Garmin 60CSx uses NMEA 0183 version 3.0.1. The Yaesu VX-8DR’s version is not published, but we can try to infer it by doing a little research on the model used in the FGPS-2. Allegedly, the unit is a Position GPS-72(C). Datasheets are hard to find from this company, but we can find a &lt;a href=&quot;http://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;amp;sl=ja&amp;amp;u=http://www.posit.co.jp/seihin/pdf/GPS-72_J.pdf&amp;amp;prev=/search%3Fq%3D%2522position%2522%2B%2522gps-72%2522%2B%252251281-0894%2522%2Bfiletype:pdf%2B-garmin%26hl%3Den%26safe%3Doff%26tbo%3Dd%26biw%3D1280%26bih%3D699&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=3RsXUfe9B4z2igLTpIDoCA&amp;amp;ved=0CDYQ7gEwAA&quot;&gt;Position GPS-72 summary sheet&lt;/a&gt; (translated, original in Japanese). Unfortunately, this doesn’t tell us what version of NMEA it supports. Let’s hope it uses something compatible with version 3.01.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here on out, you need to understand that every NMEA sentence needs to include a carriage return (CR) and line feed (LF) at the end of each transmission. This is equivalent to hitting ENTER in a terminal session, assuming your application settings are correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vx-8dr-nmea-handshake&quot;&gt;VX-8DR NMEA Handshake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at what the VX-8DR sends us first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$PSRF106,21*0F
$PSRF103,0,0,1,1*25
$PSRF103,1,0,0,1*25
$PSRF103,2,0,0,1*26
$PSRF103,3,0,0,1*27
$PSRF103,4,0,2,1*22
$PSRF103,5,0,0,1*21
$PSRF103,8,0,0,1*2C
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nmea-address-field&quot;&gt;NMEA Address Field&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$PSRFnnn: The first field is called the “address”, and it is broken down as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$: The first character in an NMEA message is either $ or !, and marks the beginning of a new sentence. $ identifies a sentence that conforms to a format of a delimited series of parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PSRF: The second character, a P, followed by a three-character manufacturer code, indicates that this is a Proprietary Address Field registered with SRF&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nmea.org/Assets/20120830%200183%20manufacturer%20codes.pdf&quot;&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;, or SiRF Technology. There are two other types of Fields: Approved Address Fields (things like GPGGA, which we sent to the radio), and Query Address Fields (which always start with a Q), which are used to ask another device to send it some information. NMEA is extremely complex in this regard. It doesn’t just support GPS (it supports things like engine room monitoring, electronic chart systems, and radar), so there are a whole host of possible commands that are perfectly valid in NMEA, but would be ignored by a device that doesn’t support them.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The VX-8DR doesn’t really have a SiRF chip inside it, although it may have code provided by SiRF. Or an engineer just emulated existing SiRF modules. There’s no way to know without having access to the firmware source code.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nnn: The proprietary message code is the remainder of the address field. It is a unique code that indicates the type of command or message being sent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proprietary-message-codes&quot;&gt;Proprietary Message Codes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;106/103: The proprietary message codes that the Yaesu advertises are as follows, and the meaning of the specific instances we received:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;106: The proprietary message code 106 is a command from the radio that specifies the GPS datum to use. 21 = WGS84&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ekf.de/c/cgps/cg2/inf/nmea_reference_manual.pdf&quot;&gt;(source)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;103: The proprietary message code 103 is a command from the radio that specifies which NMEA messages to send and how often&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpsinformation.org/dale/nmea.htm&quot;&gt;(source)&lt;/a&gt;. 0=GGA, 1=GLL, 2=GSA, 3=GSV, 4=RMC, 5=VTG, 8=ZDA (if 1PPS output is supported)&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ekf.de/c/cgps/cg2/inf/nmea_reference_manual.pdf&quot;&gt;(sup)&lt;/a&gt;. The second field (0) is SetRate, the third (1, 0, 2) is the rate in seconds, and the fourth enables (1) or disables (0) the checksum. The number after the asterisk ( * ) is the checksum for the command.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handshake sentences that the Yaesu VX-8DR sends mean it is asking the GPS receiver to use GPS datum WGS84, to transmit GGA every second, to transmit RMC every 2 seconds, and to send a checksum with those messages. We don’t know whether other messages would normally be passed between the FGPS-2 and the VX-8DR, for example to negotiate a different baud rate, so we can’t assume it’s safe to use messages other than the ones it advertises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, we know that the unit may support other messages, but it is expecting GGA and RMC to update its information. So let’s look at what those two sentences look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gpgga-messages---gps-time-position-and-fix-data&quot;&gt;$GPGGA Messages - GPS Time, Position, and Fix Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the handshake, these sentences follow a fixed format as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, we have an address. This time it is an Approved Address Field. Approved Address Fields beginning with GP indicate the position is GPS based. GGA is the Sentence Formatter, specifically, the GPS Fix Data Sentence Formatter. GGA retrieves time, position, and fix related data for a GPS receiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be formatted like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$--GGA,hhmmss.ss,llll.ll,a,yyyyy.yy,a,x,xx,x.x,x.x,M,x.x,M,x.x,xxxx*hh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also must be terminated with a Line-Feed and Carriage-Return character – in our terminal emulator, this is the equivalent of hitting the ENTER key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;our-garmin-gpgga-sample&quot;&gt;Our Garmin $GPGGA Sample&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down what we sent. The format of the GGA messages should be as follows, and I’ve broken down the message we were sending.&lt;a href=&quot;http://aprs.gids.nl/nmea/&quot;&gt;(source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,013622,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,09,0.9,00078,M,0020,M,,*49
$GPGGA,hhmmss.ss,llll.ll,a,yyyyy.yy,a,x,xx,x.x,x.x,M,x.x,M,x.x,xxxx*kk`
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPGGA,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;hhmmss.ss = UTC of position&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;013622,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;llll.ll = latitude of position&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1234.5678,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;a = N or S&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;N,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;yyyyy.yy = Longitude of position&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12345.6789,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;a = E or W&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;W,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x = GPS Quality indicator (0=no fix, 1=GPS fix, 2=Dif. GPS fix)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;xx = number of satellites in use&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;09,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x.x = horizontal dilution of precision&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.9,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x.x = Antenna altitude above mean-sea-level&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;00078,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;M = units of antenna altitude, meters&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;M,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x.x = Geoidal separation&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0020,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;M = units of geoidal separation, meters&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;M,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;x.x = Age of Differential GPS data (seconds)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;xxxx = Differential reference station ID&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;*49&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;kk = checksum&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that the spec says .ss, .ll, and .yy are all optional, and there are no minimum or maximum requirements on precision. Leading 0s are always required to maintain fixed length. For variables numbers (such as altitude or dilution of precision), the decimal point and decimal fractions are also optional. At this point, our sentence appears to conform to the specification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the sentence we sent the Yaesu was valid, but it did not extract the altitude data from the message, that must mean the VX-8DR does not conform to the NMEA standard. That is bad – it means that now we have to figure out what the Yaesu is expecting. (This is also a poor engineering choice. Cutting corners happens all the time in software engineering, but when you have a closed interface and proprietary hardware that magically work with the device, this kind of choice is exactly how you keep it closed. Some frustrated part of me wants to say this was intentional, and that a product manager at Yaesu chose to lock consumers into their hardware to make more profit.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll have to figure that sentence structure out later. Thankfully others have already done part of the job. We’ll come back to that, but we have one more required and advertised sentence to examine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gprmc-messages---gnss-time-date-position-course-and-speed&quot;&gt;$GPRMC Messages - GNSS Time, Date, Position, Course, and Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RMC, Recommended Minimum Specific GNSS Data, retrieves time, date, position, course, and speed data. RMC is unique in that it is often accompanied by RMB, which handles destination waypoints. This isn’t required by the Yaesu, and there’s no advertisement that it is supported either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format for RMC messages is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$--RMC,hhmmss.ss,A,llll.ll,a,yyyyy.yy,a,x.x,x.x,xxxxxx,x.x,a,a*hh
1 = UTC of position fix
2 = Data status (V=navigation receiver warning)
3 = Latitude of fix
4 = N or S
5 = Longitude of fix
6 = E or W
7 = Speed over ground in knots
8 = Track made good in degrees True
9 = UT date
10 = Magnetic variation degrees (Easterly var. subtracts from true course)
11 = E or W
12 = Checksum
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the spec optionality, precision, and padding requirements stay the same. Let’s try sending a message to the Yaesu. We’ll start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,013622,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,09,0.9,00078,M,0020,M,,*49
$GPRMC,013622,A,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,1.1,63.5,100213,17.4,E,D*0F
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same result as before. Garbage on the screen, and more importantly, speed is not displayed, which was a crucial part of GPRMC. The Yaesu does not conform with these messages either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-it-doesnt-conform-what-is-the-right-way-to-do-it&quot;&gt;If it doesn’t conform, what is the right way to do it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I’m wishing I had that $160 GPS module. I would hook it up and sniff the messages between the VX-8DR and the FGPS-2, because there may be 1) more to the handshake than we witnessed, and 2) some unique formatting the Yaesu expects NMEA messages to be in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others have picked up on 2), as we’ll see shortly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vx8r-yahoo-group&quot;&gt;VX8R Yahoo Group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some very useful information can be gleaned from the work of others. In particular, &lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.yahoo.com/group/VX8R/message/1208&quot;&gt;EA2CXK posted&lt;/a&gt; some extremely helpful information. In particular, some sample raw messages from the FGPS-2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,123223.000,30,10,2011,,*55
$GPGGA,123223.000,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,1,04,02.7,00123.4,M,0051.7,M,000.0,0000*41
$GPRMC,123223.000,A,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,0000.00,291.33,301011,,*3E
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, the Yaesu &lt;strong&gt;does&lt;/strong&gt; expect a certain format for its messages. Let’s compare these with our original Garmin messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Message Type&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Source&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sentence&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPGGA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,013622,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,09,0.9,00078,M,0020,M,,*49&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,123223.000,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,1,04,02.7,00123.4,M,0051.7,M,000.0,0000*41&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPRMC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,013622,A,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,1.1,63.5,100213,17.4,E,D*0F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,123223.000,A,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,0000.00,291.33,301011,,*3E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPZDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;We don&#39;t have one!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,123223.000,30,10,2011,,*55&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This right here is what we’re looking for, as it tells us way more than any NMEA specification, or any GPS module datasheet can. Three sample lines from the FGPS-2 tell us exactly the format that the Yaesu is expecting to receive. If we can force all of our data into this format, we can communicate with the Yaesu. Let’s look at it in detail to figure out the Yaesu VX-8DR NMEA format. Thank you Toni, EA2CXK, for posting what was missing in dozens of other forum and blog posts! If I ever hear you on air, I must thank you in person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s proof that it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/yaesu/Yaesu_Good_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Yaesu VX-8DR showing GPS status after correctly receiving a properly formatted GPS NMEA string over a serial TTL connection.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yaesu-vx-8dr-gpgga-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPGGA NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yaesu VX-8DR expects $GPGGA messages to follow the following format. This no longer follows the NMEA standard, so every character listed must be present. Numbers must be padded on the left with extra 0s to fill in any free spaces. Decimal fractions must be padded on the right with extra 0s to fill in any free spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,hhmmss.sss,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,x,xx,xx.x,xxxxx.x,M,xxxx.x,M,xxx.x,xxxx*hh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that, essentially, the Yaesu expects padded numbers of greater precision and magnitude than our Garmin was presenting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got curious, though, and changed the checksum to 00 on my messages. Guess what? The Yaesu still took them. Checksum can be anything. So instead of having to recalculate checksum after modifying the sentence, we can just set checksum to anything and the Yaesu should accept it. I say should because I haven’t tested this thoroughly, but I’m optimistic this will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yaesu-vx-8dr-gprmc-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPRMC NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yaesu VX-8DR expects $GPRMC sentences to follow the following format. The same caveats from $GPGGA apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,hhmmss.sss,A,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,xxxx.xx,xxx.xx,xxxxxx,,*hh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, the Yaesu expects different padding. It is important to note that the Yaesu message also omits magnetic variation and mode indicator, and truncates one parameter position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yaesu-vx-8dr-gpzda-nmea-sentence-syntax&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR $GPZDA NMEA Sentence Syntax&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We never talked about this one. ZDA is the “Time &amp;amp; Date” command, and the Garmin never sent it, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt;, the Yaesu did say it supported it, even if it said it didn’t require it to be sent. ZDA is the only command that we’ve seen so far that sends a date, which is extremely useful if we want to set a the time on a device that communicates with a GPS receiver. This is a pretty awesome thing for the Yaesu, because it is difficult to set the time on the thing because the manual is wrong. You can see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldwidedx.com/handitalkies/36965-vx-8r-setting-time-how.html&quot;&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; for information on how to set the time manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yaesu VX-8DR expects $GPZDA sentences to follow the following format. The same caveats from $GPGGA apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,hhmmss.sss,xx,xx,xxxx,,*hh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is beautiful. It supports date and time. It doesn’t support local time zone (hours and minutes), but that’s OK, because the Yaesu makes us set it manually in APRS option menu 25 - TIME ZONE anyways, if we want to use GPS time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use GPS time on the VX-8DR, go to the APRS screens by pressing MENU from your TXO screens, enter the menu by holding down MENU for a second or two, and use the dial knob to select option 17 - GPS TIME SET. Press MENU to enter this menu item, use the dial wheel to select AUTO, and press MENU to save. Use the dial to scroll to 25 - TIME ZONE, press MENU to enter this menu item, use the dial wheel to select the UTC offset in hours and minutes, and press MENU to save. Hold down MENU for one to two seconds to exit the menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you send a ZDA message to the radio after setting these options, the radio will automatically set its time. If your GPS is not sending time as UTC, you may need to fiddle with your time zone settings to get the radio to show the right time, or fiddle with your intermediary interface to shift the time before sending it to the Yaesu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Also, if you decide to play with your 16 - GPS DATUM settings, be aware that if you aren’t currently connected to GPS, it may cease to let you change it again. When this happened, and I got stuck in the ‘Tokyo Mean’ datum, I panicked a little – would I have to wipe my unit and reprogram it? What if that didn’t work? If you get in this position, send another series of valid GPS sentences to the radio, go into the menu while it still says it can see satellites, and you can change it again.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-different-is-the-yaesu-from-the-garmin&quot;&gt;How different is the Yaesu from the Garmin?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a visualization, to help make it clearer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Message&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Source&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sentence&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPGGA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,013622____,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,2,09,_0.9,00078__,M,0020__,M,_____,____*49&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,123223.000,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,1,04,02.7,00123.4,M,0051.7,M,000.0,0000*41&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,hhmmss.sss,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,x,xx,xx.x,xxxxx.x,M,xxxx.x,M,xxx.x,xxxx*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPRMC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,013622____,A,1234.5678,N,12345.6789,W,___1.1_,_63.5_,100213,17.4,E,D*0F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,123223.000,A,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,0000.00,291.33,301011,,*3E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,$GPRMC,hhmmss.sss,A,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,xxxx.xx,xxx.xx,xxxxxx,,*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPZDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Garmin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;We don&#39;t have one!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FGPS-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,123223.000,30,10,2011,,*55&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,hhmmss.sss,xx,xx,xxxx,,*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-those-other-messages-the-yaesu-supports&quot;&gt;What about those other messages the Yaesu supports?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, earlier, the Yaesu told us (via $PSRF103 sentences) that it supports certain NMEA sentences. Specifically, it supports these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;NMEA Code&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sentence Formatter&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;NMEA Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Available Data&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GGA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Global Positioning System Fix Data&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Time, Position, Fix Status&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GLL&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Geographic Position - Latitude/Longitude&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Latitude, Longitude, time, status, and mode indicator&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GSA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GNSS DOP and Active Satellites&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GNSS receiver operating mode, satellites used in the navigation solution, and dilution of precision&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GSV&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GNSS Satellites in View&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;# of satellites in view, satellite ID numbers, elevation, azimuth, and SNR value&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RMC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Recommended Minimum Specific GNSS Data&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Time, date position, course, speed, magnetic variation, mode indicator&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;VTG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Course Over Ground and Ground Speed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Actual course and speed relative to the ground, and mode indicator&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ZDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Time &amp;amp; Date&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;UTC, day, month, year, and local time zone&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave it to somebody else to figure these out, until I get my solution built. It’s very possible that, despite the lack of examples, these sentences could be sent to the Yaesu in some meaningful way, for example the dilution of precision, or satellite data. I don’t know enough about APRS yet to understand whether it’s possible to include this information with your APRS packets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now know how to connect to and send a properly formatted GPS NMEA message to the Yaesu VX-8DR. Here’s the summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9600baud TTL 3.3V serial signalling, 8/N/1
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; RS232 5V signalling – you need a level converter if that’s all you have&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3-wire physical interface to the following pins:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Pin#&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;GPS Side Purpose&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Yaesu Side Purpose&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GPS RX&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yaesu TX&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GPS TX&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yaesu RX&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;GPS GND&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yaesu GND&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The messages need to be formatted exactly as follows:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Message&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Source&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Sentence&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPGGA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sample&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,123223.000,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,1,04,02.7,00123.4,M,0051.7,M,000.0,0000*41&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPGGA,hhmmss.sss,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,x,xx,xx.x,xxxxx.x,M,xxxx.x,M,xxx.x,xxxx*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPRMC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sample&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,123223.000,A,4131.2334,N,00021.1216,E,0000.00,291.33,301011,,*3E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPRMC,hhmmss.sss,A,llll.llll,a,yyyyy.yyyy,a,xxxx.xx,xxx.xx,xxxxxx,,*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$GPZDA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sample&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,123223.000,30,10,2011,,*55&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Syntax&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;$GPZDA,hhmmss.sss,xx,xx,xxxx,,*hh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Yaesu may support other messages, in specific formats, TBD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Garmin GPSMAP 60CSx does not support TTL messaging at 9600 baud, nor does it support the proprietary NMEA sentence formats that the Yaesu expects. In order for me to go any further, I will need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construct an interface proxy that has RS232 @ 4800 baud on one end and TTL @ 9600 baud on the other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorporate a micro-controller that can rewrite the NMEA sentences between the Yaesu and a GPS receiver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out whether I want to power the microcontroller separately, such as with battery power, or invest money in the CT-M11 cable which outputs 3.3V from the VX-8DR, which should be sufficient to power, say, an ATtiny. (If I can source one that can support two serial interfaces, that is.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will have to wait until next time. I hope you find this useful. This research took about 10 hours in a single day of hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;yaesu-vx-8dr-nmea-controller&quot;&gt;Yaesu VX-8DR NMEA Controller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier we wanted to know what kind of NMEA chip this thing has. There’s a service manual floating around for this unit. It indicates that the serial/microphone port connects to a board labeled CNTL-2 Unit, from which the GPS pins go to lines ‘GPS_TXD’ and ‘GPS_RXD’ – which connect to pin K7 (RXD) and pin K6 (TXD) of IC HD64F2370VLP Q9024. This IC is identified elsewhere as a Renesas 16-Bit Single-Chip Microcomputer H8S Family/H8S/2300 Series. What does this mean? NMEA support is emulated in a microcontroller, and there’s no easy way to dig further on this device. That was a dead end. (Unless we can somehow extract and reverse engineer the microcontroller firmware.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can take a parallel approach and look at the VX-8GR – it has an integrated GPS module, and it is remotely possible that the FGPS-2 and VX-8GR have the same GPS module inside. (&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; They don’t, though, I found out later. The unit in the FGPS-2 is the Position GPS-72, and the unit inside the VX-8GR is the Position GPS-76. This according to an obscure reference in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arifidenza.it/forum/pop_printer_friendly.asp?ARCHIVE=true&amp;amp;TOPIC_ID=161925&quot;&gt;Italian forum posting&lt;/a&gt;. It’s possible they are similar enough that this doesn’t matter, though.) The GPS unit sits in the place where the VX-8DR’s microphone/GPS connector is, and its internal connector feeds into the CNTL board on the VX-8GR labeled J2006. Its pins are connected to GPS TXD, GPS RXD, GND, LPCTL, GPS 3V, and BACKUP 3V. GPS TXD and GPS RXD connect to the same pins on the microcontroller as the VX-8DR. The block diagram indicates the GPS antenna is AT7001, and the exploded parts diagram calls it out as Q7000642. Since these are internal part numbers, they don’t do us much good. That was a dead end. (Unless we can get someone to disassemble their VX-8GR and take photos of their GPS module.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no easy way to find out what version of NMEA the VX-8DR (or VX-8GR) support. (Until Yaesu support gets back to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 18:09:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2013/02/09/reverse-engineering-yaesu-vx-8dr-gps-interface.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2013/02/09/reverse-engineering-yaesu-vx-8dr-gps-interface.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Feature Detection in the Visual Pattern Recognition of Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a guest lecture in Dr Thomas Dieterich’s class on Linguistics and Cognitive Science at PSU on The Visual Pattern Recognition of Reading. To that end, I released the paper I wrote in 2008 on the topic, as well as my slides and notes, into the Creative Commons. FWIW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:#CCCCFF;width:70%;margin-left:15%;padding:3px;border:1px solid gray;&quot;&gt;
&lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Creative Commons License&quot; style=&quot;border-width:0&quot; src=&quot;http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/88x31.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span xmlns:dc=&quot;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/&quot; property=&quot;dc:title&quot;&gt;Evidence and Consequences of Feature Detection in The Visual Pattern Recognition of Reading&lt;/span&gt; by &lt;a xmlns:cc=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/ns#&quot; href=&quot;http://www.lingnik.com/visual-pattern-recognition&quot; property=&quot;cc:attributionName&quot; rel=&quot;cc:attributionURL&quot;&gt;Taylor J. Meek&lt;/a&gt; is licensed under a &lt;a rel=&quot;license&quot; href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 United States License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;These original publications may be accessed electronically from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lingnik.com/visual-pattern-recognition&quot;&gt;http://www.lingnik.com/visual-pattern-recognition&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;files&quot;&gt;Files:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-and-reading-cc.pdf&quot;&gt;Evidence and Consequences of Feature Detection in the Visual Pattern Recognition of Reading (2008)&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 2.42MB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-handout-cc.pdf&quot;&gt;Pattern Recognition Handout&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 301.59KB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-slides-color-cc.pdf&quot;&gt;Visual Pattern Recognition Color&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 5.87MB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-slides-color-cc.pptx&quot;&gt;Visual Pattern Recognition Color&lt;/a&gt; (PPTX, 5.01MB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-slides-highcontrast-cc.pdf&quot;&gt;Visual Pattern Recognition High Contrast&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, 5.8MB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-visual-pattern-recognition-slides-highcontrast-cc.pptx&quot;&gt;Visual Pattern Recognition High Contrast&lt;/a&gt; (PPTX, 4.96MB)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2009 14:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2009/10/19/visual-pattern-recognition.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2009/10/19/visual-pattern-recognition.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Fast(er) Transact-SQL String Split() Function</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2014-05-07:&lt;/strong&gt; Aaron Bertrand put this topic to bed &lt;a href=&quot;http://sqlperformance.com/2012/07/t-sql-queries/split-strings&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft SQL Server 2005 has no SPLIT(InputString,Delimiter) function. For example, if you had some CSV (comma-separated-values) data like ‘Toyota,Tacoma,2009,$20000’, there is no built-in way in Transact-SQL to split that up into its discrete parts. There are other solutions out there that attempt to split this data up for you into either a table like (ColumnNumber Integer,ColumnData VarChar) with each row being a column in your single string, and then letting you PIVOT those into columns (CarMfg,CarMake,CarYear,CarCost).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other functions out there that I could find would iterate through the entire string character-by-character, seeking the next instance of @Delimiter within @InputString, marking that point, and using SUBSTRING() to go backwards in the string to the previous instance of @Delimiter to retrieve the string. Each time it found a delimiter, it would insert the column value and column number into a table variable @ResultTable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works for small strings, but as the length of each column within your string grows, this method becomes inefficient, especially when you’re working with a large number of strings. My solution addresses this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;DECLARE @ResultTable TABLE (Col Integer, Val VarChar(255));
DECLARE @InputString VarChar(8000);
DECLARE @Delimiter VarChar(50);
SET @InputString = &#39;1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,0&#39;;
SET @Delimiter = &#39;,&#39;;
----
DECLARE @Start Integer, @NextDelimiter Integer, @Length Integer, @Number Integer;
SET @InputString = @InputString %2B @Delimiter;
SET @Number = 1;
SET @Start = 1;
SET @Length = CHARINDEX(@Delimiter,@InputString,0) - 1;
WHILE @Start
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my results from testing these two methods:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fields&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rows&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;FieldLength&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Intarweb Method&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;My Method&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;17s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;26s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;17s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;149s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;22s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;61s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;56s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;200s&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;116s&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, when the size of each column is the same, there really is no benefit, and as the number of columns grows, it does so exponentially. However, with the method described earlier, as the size of each column grows, it just gets ugly.  &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2009 04:12:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2009/10/16/a-faster-transact-sql-string-split-function.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2009/10/16/a-faster-transact-sql-string-split-function.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vowel Inventory Formant Mapping with Praat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2008, as a project for my Applied Linguistics inventory course, I looked at the possibility of automating Praat to find and map the vowel inventory of an individual. The files below represent the entirety of that work, which was inconclusive, though it represents one method of extracting formants from Praat into Excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;files&quot;&gt;Files:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-praat-formants-paper.pdf&quot;&gt;Semi-Automated Formant Extraction with Praat&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-praat-formants-bruce42column1.pdf&quot;&gt;Appendix: Formant Plot&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-praat-formants-bruce42column1.xlsx&quot;&gt;Appendix: Formant Plot&lt;/a&gt; (XLSX)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-praat-formants-extract-formants-tabbed-fast.praat&quot;&gt;Praat Script - Fast&lt;/a&gt; (.praat file)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lingnik.com/assets/taylor-meek-praat-formants-extract-formants-tabbed-slow.praat&quot;&gt;Praat Script - Slow&lt;/a&gt; (.praat file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2009 14:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2009/06/02/formant-extraction-with-praat.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2009/06/02/formant-extraction-with-praat.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Replacing an LCD or Laptop CCFL backlight tube/bulb</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What to do when your Laptop or LCD screen/laptop screen goes dark, black, red, orange, or any other annoying color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2014-05-07:&lt;/strong&gt; I wrote this a long time ago, and there are much clearer instructions (with pictures) elsewhere. Reader be warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2004-09-23:&lt;/strong&gt; I have actually replaced my own bulb some time ago! A while after posting this, I found a source for CCFL lamps–&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mouser.com/&quot;&gt;Mouser Electronics&lt;/a&gt;, based out of Texas. With a catalog the size of a small metro phonebook, they have everything. Soooo. Couple of things: Make /sure/ that you measure your old bulb precisely. Anticipate that the new bulb will have flared tips at both ends. Be gentle when bending the leads, and make certain you form them properly if the old leads were shaped strangely. These little guys are cheaper than expected–less than $20 including shipping for a bulb. That’s about it. Email me if you have more questions, or concerns. Good luck!
* x&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--adsense-ccfl1--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-story&quot;&gt;The Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some number of years ago, my father gave me his old work laptop. It was a home-style laptop. A Compaq Presario 1681. Compaqs, I have since determined, are not going to be a sort of computer I will ever purchase myself. This system, I should say now, has had numerous issues. But anyways. After using this system extensively, in a manner which was not prescribe by the surgeon general (long nights hacking beauticious MUSHcode, and leaving it on as a -server- under linux), it began to develop issues. First was the screen going floppy on me, which was annoying and mechanical. I’m not good at mechanical, and to this day, it is still floppy. It has no tension in one of the feet which clamp onto the skeleton of the laptop body. I guess the gear-teeth got stripped, from what I can tell. Other issues developed, which next included the screen itself–the subject of this text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was an annoying thing. The laptop’s LCD screen turned orange-red. Not completely. I mean, you could still -read- everything just fine. Just that everything had an orange hue. Not only is this annoying, but it is most likely unhealthy for you. (Your eyes are not used to staring at one hue for hours at a time, I imagine.) I dealt with it by attaching an external monitor. And then the system began overheating more and more, and finally melted its own solder, on the DC jack. Hence, she died, and was shelved for some number of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most computers in this situation, with most owners, this would mean the end of a potentially useful life. A computer without a use is landfill. But then, a few weeks ago (as of this writing, 10/4/2003), around the beginning of September, I was rummaging through my garage, looking for a stereo y-adapter (which I never did find) for hooking various sound sources together. And then I found the old laptop. Dusty, stuffed haphazardly in a box of miscellanous other computer-related things. And so I get brave. I pulled her out, as well as her AC adapters, and began messing about with it in my room. Obviously, the power had long drained out of her batteries, and since the AC adapters didn’t work (her solder melted. Remember?), I was left with one choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay. Well. I should regress, and note now. I had two choices. I could have shipped her off for repairs; but I’m cheap, and I know I’ll get charged anally. So that left me with fixing it myself. This in and of itself consisted of prying her apart, and carefully removing each and every part of her chassis to get to the motherboard, which itself was nigh impossible to remove. (I’ll do disassembly instructions, some day, maybe.) Finally, with that removed, I worked at resoldering the DC jack properly. That finish, reassembly was a breeze, and she charged to a full 100% within the hour. I was very pleased. Finally, she booted up, and I was greeted with an orange-on-darker-orange version of ‘COMPAQ’ as her BIOS snappily shifted bits and bytes about. And then she bit me. She had no functional bootloaded; but that didn’t matter right now. I would later reinstall Windows 95, and then upgrade to 98. But that was some time later. What struck me, as I stared at a blank screen, with a single underscore in the corner, was how orange everything was. And then I felt inspired to fix that, before doing anything else to her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at this point that I briefly installed Linux and such, so that I could open an image editor (the Gimp), to throw some color bars on the screen. I took out my prismacolors, and drew identical bars on a sheet of white paper, held it up to the screen, and took a digital picture. (available at the link below) Just for proof. And comparison. Then I got to the real work. Turning her off, pulling her battery, and making to to have discharged anything nasty in my body, I began prying the LCD screen off. I first detached it from the body itself. (her feet brackets were removed by their screws, and any cables/sheet-cables were removed from the main system) I then proceeded to remove the front bezel-panel from the LCD (there were four screws, covered by rubber feet), to give access to the LCD panel and circuitry proper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who has never seen the inside of one, they are rather simple. Mine, being for a laptop, also had a microphone mounted inside, but other than that and its cable, the guts were the LCD screen itself (surrounded by a hard metal bezel), the cable attached to it, the inverter board (I’ll explain later) and the cables to it. It’s a very neat package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways. After that was done, I dismantled the LCD screen after removing it from the screen body itself, and finally got to the backlight tube. (This was a very hard thing to get to.) Finally, I removed the tube from the reflector, attached it to the inverter board, attached the board to the laptop, and turned it on with only those two things connected. Sure enough. I had an orange backlight tube. At this point, I should explain that this is wrong. This backlight tube should, ideally, be pure white, without variance (though each manufacturer will design their LCD screen to varying definitions of ‘pure white,’ thereby lending any screen with a replaced CCFL tube a slight color variance) so that your screen colors (produced by the liquid-crystal color pixels) are represented naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, having determined that the source of the problem is most likely the tube itself (which are usually rated for around 20,000 hours or so of operation), and not the inverter board (which output variable voltage; a voltage drop should not change the color of the tube. only the brightness), it’s time to find a new tube. This, however, I will warn you, is not easy. In three days of researching that very thing, and nothing else, I found nothing useful. I found one or two merchants online that would, naturally, take your LCD and replace it for you at a figure of $99 or so. If you aren’t comfortable doing this operation yourself, I’d suggest finding such a place, and paying the $99. (Try my links section below.) It really isn’t worth damaging a $300 LCD panel over a thing that is 250mm long by 3mm in diameter. ;P But me, I want to replace it myself. And nobody in known existance seems to sell them, by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the next logical step, and tried the local stores in town. Most notably were Radio Shack (who is an authorized HP repair center, btw; they handle the Compaq laptops, too. But not in-house, which is what I need.), who wasn’t able to sell me or order the lamp by itself. The store manager wasn’t even nice about it. So I’m not returning there ever again. The second place I went was a local electronics supply store that is housed in a warehouse, called Norvac Electronics. If you’re ever in need of electronics supplies, and you live in the Northwest in an area with one of these, go there. They certainly had more than I expected them to have. In fact, they even had CCFL lamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t think it was that easy, though. Their lamps were too big. How? Too big around, in diameter. The lamp reflector housing was too small for the lamps they sold, so I walked out empty-handed. (excluding my laptop; they were nice enough to let me dismantle it in-store for explanation and to try to see if it would work.) I was at a loss. Nowhere else in town had them, and I couldn’t find them online. I could find vague references to cost, but none of them would work. It sounded like it would be a cheap operation. Something like $8-30 for a single tube. That’s all I needed. I just needed to find a place that had them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a month passes, and I took the computer apart and made it into a simple box with an external monitor, so that I could at least use it without wasting the hours of life for the LCD screen itself. Or the inverter, or anything else like that. It’s sitting on a speaker right now, hooked up to everything, without its top cover, with its components exposed. WHEE. I pulled up google a few hours ago, and typed in my search string.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lo and behold, something comes up. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jkllamps.com&quot;&gt;JKL Lamps Corporation&lt;/a&gt;. (“If it lights, and you need it, we have it!”) This is a company that produces and distributes miniature lamps (of the old visible filament style), laptop ccfls, various other ccfls, UV ccfls, and inverters for above. And what do you know, they have a product listing with pictures right on their page. With pdf catalogs. And links to their ditributors, which allow online ordering. I am shocked, and very pleased. Plus here’s the greatest part: The prices for the tubes are $15 for the most expensive type they have , with $10.29 being the cheapest (and for most of them, I should say) each. Now, the only problem is that they list them by specification, and I don’t have the specifications for my current lamp. But I know who will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturer of my inverter board. Dissecting it from my LCD screen once more, I gaze over it carefully for a long time. (I can’t tell if there is a capacitor in it or not, though I assume if there is it is discharged) Markings on the back indicate ‘Delta,’ and so I pull a google on Delta Electronics. Instantly, I come up with a Taiwanese company that produces a number of electronics components. And after some searching, I find the inverters. I know who made it, for sure. And after peering over their parts listing, I peer at the part no. on my board, and search for that. No luck. It doesn’t appear to be manufactured anymore. (This laptop is old. ‘97, at best.) I sent an e-mail tonight to their US technical support rep, requesting specifications on this very board. I’ll have to wait until next week for a response, though. However, I did find a similar part-numbered component on their site, and so I may base my tube decision on that if I receive no response, or no help. (Really, I can make a best guess anyways. There aren’t many choices for the length I need.) So once I get the specifications, I’ll be able to order the lamp from one of JKL’s distributors, get it, and simply install it. That’s it. From reading the instructions on several other websites about replacing them, I may or may not have to resolder the leads to the lamp to the inverter board connector. No biggie there, though. Once that’s done, I should have a perfectly functional laptop LCD screen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming, of course, that the inverter board isn’t bad. But then, at least I know who manufactures them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--adsense-ccfl2--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anatomy-of-an-lcd-screen-for-laptops&quot;&gt;Anatomy of an LCD Screen (for laptops)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A laptop LCD screen is comprised of several basic elements. As a whole, you have your LCD screen itself, a backlight bulb, and an inverter. (Not counting the controller boards and such for controlling your video.) LCD screens will always vary. Configurations are wide and broad. In general, though, they will always have the above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lcd&quot;&gt;LCD&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LCD screen itself is what presents the image. With no power to the monitor, you have a black screen, which looks really slick. It is comprised of several layers of various elements, housed in a metal bezel. Either on the sides, or the top/bottom of the screen, a reflector is mounted with the backlight. The elements of the LCD screen include (from back to front, visually), the mirror/reflector of the backlight. Usually a very high-reflective metal, or similar setup; sometimes, the mirror may be the only source of light, and there will be no secondary light source. This is why some LCD screens do not work in the dark. On top of the mirror is a polarization filter (to only allow light to pass in one direction), and then a sheet of glass (or some transparent polymer). Next is one of the most important components. Essentially, there are two sheets of transparent electrodes, with liquid crystal sandwiched between them. These many, many electrodes will change the orientation of the crystals, to allow/disallow light to pass through them. (Because of this orientation, this is also why LCD screens will appear to be in odd colors, or darker, when viewed at non-standard angles. The properly orientated crystals will now be under the wrong colors, or orientated in such a way so as not to allow the light to shine any way but directly forward.) On top of the outer layer of transparent electrodes is another sheet of glass or polymer, with a polarized filter on it. You may or may not have another layer on top of this, for simple protection purposes. The rear sheet of glass, before the mirror, will be made with various different methods. Either it will be constructed in such a way so as to diffuse the light evenly from the rear over the entire pane with methods I don’t entirely understand myself, or it will just be opaque on one side (generally, the side opposite the mirror), hence diffusing naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you can get gray shades by making the crystals only change orientation partially. (Hence allowing x% of the light to go through; otherwise it’s 0% or 100%.) You can get color by adding more filter layers. (IE, the three primaries used,arranged each as a pixel, with each color affected by a electrode.) An interesting note is that you can use a magnifying glass to view the spaces between where the electrodes operate. They appear black. Also, the layout of the color pixels is RGB; Red-Green-Blue. The same theory applies to regular CRTs; only they use an electron gun and I don’t really know what else. Anyways. The only other parts of your screen are the various controller boards, which vary by manufacturer. These control which pixels do what. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;backlight&quot;&gt;Backlight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The backlight is just a fluorescent lamp. Basically. The technical name for it, generally, is the Cold Cathode Fluorescent Lamp, or CCFL. It is this lamp which brightens your screen in the dark. (There is another kind found in older PDAs and watches, called Electroluminescant; but that relies on a different method.) The lamp(s) will be mounted on the top and bottom of your screen, or on the sides. If you only have one, chances are it will be on top. With most screens, the CCFL will be part of the LCD screen itself; in others, it will be removable easily with only a screw. The lamp(s) will be as long as the screen is wide, or tall. Occasionally, two lamps will be placed side-by-side. The lamps themselves are comprised of the glass, filled with whatever gasses the manufacturer filled it with. There is no filament inside, meaning they will last a lot longer than typical ‘hot’ neon fluorescent lamps. At either end will be a lead wire. If there are two tubes, they will be daisy-chained. Otherwise, one wire will loop back towards where the first terminates. These two wires are then mounted into a plug which attaches to the inverter board. These lamps, it is worth mentioning now, are extremely high voltage. The highest I’ve found was 1,820V@5mA(Start)-810V@5mA. Be careful. Not only here, but with the LCD itself, as it can contain high voltages as well. The backlight will be mounted inside a metal reflector, which is then attached to the inside of the LCD. Basically, the reflector bounces any light from the CCFL that doesn’t go directly into the LCD, back into the LCD. It is highly reflective; hence, you should wear gloves or something similar if you are going to mess with it. And that’s it. The light, being extremely bright as compared to your standard fluorescent lamp. (~32,000Cd./m2) They are very fragile, being ~3mm in diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inverter-board&quot;&gt;Inverter Board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of your LCD panel screen is the inverter board for your CCFL. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.interq.or.jp/japan/se-inoue/e_ckt8.htm&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a basic diagram for a DC/AC inverter. One thing to note, from what I understand, is that these inverters are not like your typical DC/ACs that may be found for 12VDC-120VAC for running household electronics in a car or somesuch. These produce an output waveform that is nearly a square wave. This is simple, and doesn’t require much to do, but for most electronics equipment, an advanced version producing a pure sine wave is required. The inverter itself just takes input 12VDC, runs it though some hoops and a transformer, and outputs your 120VAC. Understand, though, that as your output (V) increases, your output (W/A) decreases. That is given a basic inverter, of course, which doesn’t deal with the things that a ccfl lamp requires. Like, for example, dimming. And nearly 2,000VAC@5mA, from a 10-20VDC input. What this means is that instead of just having your input DC%2B and ground, there are extra pinouts. For an inverter board similar to mine, it has two 18.0V ± 10% inputs and two grounds. That provides the main power. Power to the inverter board itself is provided by a 5V On/0V Off input. Dimming is controlled with the BL-Adj pin, at 1.0V ~ 5.0V. And of course, the high voltage DC output pin, and the return pin. Boards may vary, but for CCFL controlling, these things are generally common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--adsense-ccfl3--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ccfl-replacement&quot;&gt;CCFL Replacement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing the CCFL is a task that may be difficult, depending on your brand of LCD screen. Basically, you’ll want to remove the external plastic cover to your monitor, to gain access to the LCD screen itself. Remove the two leadwires from the inverter board. (Which should have a small transformer on it, two output wires, and somewhere around six input wires that go to some power source; whether it be the computer, or the main power source of the screen.) If you are able, at this point, to simply pull the CCFL/reflector out, do so carefully, being careful not to snag the wires on anything. If you aren’t able to do this yet, you’ll need to disassemble the LCD panel itself by removing, first, the metal bezel, and gaining access to the metal reflector that houses your CCFL tube. The reflector will usually have small rubber/silicone mounts that will keep the tube firmly in place. The next step is to replace the tube in the reflector. If your new tube has a new connector already, then all you need to do is place this new tube into the reflector. Otherwise, carefully desolder the old connector from the old tube, and solder it to the new tube. You may need to cut (with a razor or exact-o) the silicone/rubber off of the old tube, and replace it on the new tube. As soon as your solder is sufficiently cool, replace the silicone/rubber, and place it back into the reflector, and assemble as need be. Please ensure that you know what you are doing with your CCFL tube. You need to get one with exacting specifications to your old one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know the specs to your old tube, you’ll need to contact the manufacturer of the inverter board. Look on it for a manufacturer name and a part number. (IE, Delta, with a D symbol in a triangle.) Contact the manufacturer, and ask them for the output AC start and lamp voltage, and current ratings for your board. Then make your purchase of CCFL tube appropriately. If you can’t find the manufacturer of your inverter board, you should contact first the manufacturer of your screen/laptop, then the manufacturer of the LCD panel itself. (Which should normally be etched, or on a sticker; as well as a part number. They may be able to help you with the specifications also.) If you are not able to locate the manufacturer of the inverter board, please remove it, take a digital picture of both the front and back of it, and contact me. I may be able to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;precautions&quot;&gt;PRECAUTIONS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please be aware that you are working with high voltages here. You should take proper precautions not to do anything stupid, like licking the inverter board. Especially if it’s turned on. It may have capacitors. It may have stored charges. So may the LCD panel. It says DANGER: HIGH VOLTAGE, for a reason, you know. I will not be held responsible for anything you do with the information I’ve provided on this page. If you don’t know what you’re doing, like I don’t, then don’t do it. Pay the $99 to have your CCFL tube replaced professionally, or just buy a brand new screen for $300. Because I won’t pay for it. Take caution, as these are sensitive electronic devices, with transistors the size of a pinhead, which could EXPLODE VIOLENTLY with a static discharge from your body, thereby ruining the need for your $10.92 CCFL tube you just bought, and necessitating a $150 Inverter board. Or worse. Wear an anti-static device, or continuously discharge your body of static by touching something grounded (a metal water pipe, et cetera, if you’re in an older home; damned new plastic pipes). BE CAREFUL with the new and old CCFL tube. THEY ARE MADE OF GLASS AND WILL HURT LIKE A MOTHER BITCH FOO IF IT BREAKS AND IMPALES YOU. Not to mention they’ll be broken, then, and useless. THEY ALSO CONTAIN TRACE AMOUNTS OF MERCURY GAS. Which makes it ILLEGAL in most places to just throw it away. Not only are these suckers deadly to you, they are deadly to the environment. Contact your local city folks to find out what to do with hazardous things such as these. Be gentle with the LCD screen as a whole. As I mentioned earlier, they are composed of GLASS LAYERS. Which means, if you push or pull to hard when trying to take it out of its mounts, you MAY BREAK IT. The first laptop I ever used had its glass fracture, and puncture the liquid-crystal element, thereby making the screen warped and defective. This happened on a trip across the country, in a U-Haul. And it was in the cab, with me. I remember it being about $700 to replace, back then. You don’t want that to happen. Do not disassemble the LCD screen any more than you have to. Only take it apart enough to remove the CCFL. If you get even a single speck of dust in one of the layers, you will have dead pixels. I guarantee it. Dead pixels can also occur if your CCFL shatters while still in the housing. This sucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know everything. I am not a certified technician. I am just a guy that knows how to fix stuff. As a result, I may not have told you everthing. By following any instructions on this page, you take full risk and responsibility for your actions, and discharge any legal right to sue me, or place blame on me for things you did. Mmmkay? kthx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools&lt;/strong&gt; There will be some tools that will come in handy during all of this. Obviously, a small phillips-head screwdriver, and a set of hex. (My laptop uses a T8 for almost all of the hex-screws. There are maybe three or four phillips in the entire system.) Keep a flathead, preferably a big mutha, on hand for prying things apart, and a small one for maneuvering the locks on cables off. Pliers are handy. Use a long strip of duct tape, doubled around so that you have two tape surfaces, and attach it to your workspace. Put your screws on it, in the order that you took them out. If you want, you can make a diagram of where the screws came from. Keep your parts organized as you take them out, and memorize how you got them out. Do not force things too hard. Tweezers are useful for some small parts, and especially for things that drop in inconvenient spots. One of my tool sets has a pair of teeny-assed pliers, about 2 1/2 inches long and with a total tip area the size of a pen point. These are handy. You’ll also have hex bolts keeping things in the air. I use pliers for these, because I don’t have a nut that fits them. Tighten these are far as you can when you put them back in. Lastly, keep a razor blade on hand, for cutting tape that may be used internally. Oh, and lest I forget: Bright lights, and a flashlight. And a lot of patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--adsense-ccfl4--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sourceslinks&quot;&gt;Sources/Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mouser.com&quot;&gt;Mouser Electronics&lt;/a&gt; - A supplier of CCFL lamps for good prices. Big catalog.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jkllamps.com&quot;&gt;JKL Lamps&lt;/a&gt; - Manufacturer of CCFL lamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright (c) 2003-2004 Taylor J. Meek All rights reserved. All sources Copyright (c) their respective owners. Compaq, NEC, Presario, JKL, et cetera, are all registered trademarks of their respective owners.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2004 05:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://lingnik.com/2004/09/23/ccfl-backlight-replacement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lingnik.com/2004/09/23/ccfl-backlight-replacement.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
